Guide to the Chinese Gaming Counters Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Chinese gaming counters
1700-1840
GEN MSS 757
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.83
(2 boxes)
This collection includes over three hundred discrete mother of pearl gaming counters handcrafted by artisans in China for use in scoring and bidding in card games in the West, circa 1700-circa 1840. The collection also includes a nearly complete set of gaming counters and an accompanying lacquer box made for William Andrew Dyer of London, England, circa 1810. Most of the gaming counters bear a coat of arms, crest, or monogram of a family or individual. Many of the gaming counters also depict Chinese scenes and figures, or representations of flowers, animals, or insects.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from W. D. Neal on the Mary Flagler Cary Fund, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
About Chinese Gaming Counters
Mother of pearl gaming counters were handcrafted by artisans in China from circa 1700 to circa 1840, for use in scoring and bidding in card games in the Western world. They were chiefly created for trade with Great Britain and, to a lesser extent, with other European countries and the United States. The gaming counters were fashioned from the nacre of large oyster shells, which imparted a metallic silvery sheen and a flat even finish to each counter. They range in shape, usually circles and parallelograms, as well as in size, usually from 26 millimeters to 35 millimeters in length and width. The gaming counters are usually inscribed with a coat of arms, crest, or monogram of a family or individual, as well as other visual decoration.
The production of mother of pearl gaming counters coincided with increased trade between the Western world and China. At that time, Western society had a fashion for playing card games, including Ombre, Quadrille and Pope Joan, which required counters for scoring. The trade in mother of pearl gaming counters continued until around 1840, when whist, which requires a different scoring method, became the most popular card game in the Western world. The production of counters gradually ceased around 1840.
Overall, gaming counters are divided into two categories: bespoke (made-to-order) counters, with the coat of arms, crest, or monogram of a family or individual; and ready-made counters. Around 1760, it became fashionable for counters to have monograms even without a crest or coat. Many of the bespoke sets accompanied orders for armorial porcelain services. Ready-made counters were also available with blank roundels for later inscription in the Western world or with non-specific heraldic representations.
Sets of counters during the first decades of the eighteenth century did not have fixed combinations of shapes or sizes to comprise a complete suite. Some of the earliest counter sets, from circa 1720 to circa 1760, include fish-shaped counters, while double fishes were produced from circa 1720 to 1730. By 1750, most sets included 140 counters in three shapes: round (20 counters), short-oblong rectangle (40 counters), and long-oblong rectangle (80 counters). Between 1785 and 1810, sets also included oval and shuttle shapes. Complete sets of gaming counters were often housed in lacquered boxes, which contained several smaller boxes, some to house gaming counters and others to hold decks of cards. Many boxes also had trays painted with court cards.
Decorative elements, borders, and edges on gaming counters can be used to date them. What follows are brief timelines for each. For further information about mother of pearl gaming counters, see Bill Neal, Chinese Mother of Pearl Gaming Counters ([Great Britain]: Chezbill, 2007).
Timeline of Decorative Elements
circa 1735: Camellia flower on versos.
circa 1740-1750: River scenes with small boats, buildings, and occasionally figures on versos. Many depict the hongs (foreign business markets) on the Pearl River in Canton.
circa 1740-1770: A simplified floral design or "sketchy flower" on versos.
circa 1750-1760: Card suits on rectos or versos.
circa 1750-1780: Depictions of "billing birds," which portray two birds touching or clasping each other's bills.
circa 1760: Floral or star designs on versos.
circa 1760-1790: Diapering patterns, also known as damask, on versos.
circa 1770-1810: Detailed flowers on versos.
circa 1790-1840: Scenes of Chinese life, which may depict scenes from traditional folk tales or poetry.
circa 1800-1840: Depictions of pagodas.
circa 1820-1840: Deep carved designs, which add depth and texture to counters.
Timeline of Border Decorations
1700-1760: Single line borders following the outline of the counter.
circa 1760-1840: "Point-in-point" borders or coils pattern borders.
circa 1770-1840: Swags or laurel borders, as well as the empty reserves (cartouches) style.
circa 1780-1840: "Queen Charlotte" border, which incorporates elongated reserves and flowers, as well as the key-fret border, which consists of repeating rectangular spirals.
circa 1790-1830: "Drilled" borders consisting of a series of concave indentations.
circa 1800-1830: "Geometric" borders, which consist of two or more concentric bands of regular geometric shapes, or the "vine and moth" or "vine and fruit" borders, which consist of a leaf scroll that follows the circumference of the counter, which is then interspersed with representations of fruit or moths.
circa 1820-1840: Drilled and fretted borders became popular in around 1820, although examples exist from as early as 1760.
Timeline of Edge Decorations
circa 1750: Elaborate Chinese-style of scroll edges.
circa 1750-1770: Wavy edges.
circa 1760: Simplified Chinese-style of scroll edges.
.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes over three hundred discrete mother of pearl gaming counters handcrafted by artisans in China for use in scoring and bidding in card games in the West from circa 1700 to circa 1840. The collection also includes a nearly complete set of gaming counters and an accompanying lacquer box made for William Andrew Dyer of London, England, circa 1810. Most of the gaming counters bear a coat of arms, crest, or monogram of a family or individual. Many of the gaming counters also depict Chinese scenes and figures, or representations of flowers, animals, or insects.
Other gaming counters with identified or attributed provenance to families and individuals chiefly in Great Britain include Queen Charlotte, consort of George III, King of Great Britain; Captain Matthew Bookey of the East India Company ship Shaftesbury, and his wife, Ann Bookey; John Drummond and Susan Fane Drummond; Charles Elphinstone, the 10th Lord Elphinstone; Lewis Alexander Grant-Ogilvy, 5th Earl of Seafield; Thomas Hislop; William Maule, 1st Earl Panmure; Hildebrand Oakes 1st Baronet of the Oakes Baronetcy, of the Army, and the Oakes Baronets, of Hereford; John Joshua Proby, 1st Earl of Carysfort; John Roberts, a director of the East India Company between 1764 to 1808; John Stewart, 7th Earl of Galloway; and James Yorke, the Bishop of Ely from 1781 to 1808.
This finding aid uses specialized heraldic terminology. An excellent source defining this terminology is available in the "Glossary" and "Dictionary of Terms Used in Heraldry" sections in Bernard Burke, The General Armory of England, Scotland, Ireland, and Wales; Comprising a Registry of Armorial Bearings from the Earliest to the Present Time (1842-1884).
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Gaming Counters with Identified or Attributed Provenance, circa 1700-1840. II. Gaming Counters with Unidentified Provenance, circa 1700-1840.
Art, Chinese; Card games; Decoration and ornament -- China; Decorative arts -- China; Gambling chips -- China; Heraldry, Ornamental; Mother-of-pearl -- China; Gaming counters; Mother of pearl; Dyer, William Andrew, ca. 1791-1872; Dyer, William Andrew, ca. 1791-1872 -- Ownership
- Gaming Counters with Identified or Attributed Provenance, circa 1700-circa 1840; Series I; 182
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by the surname of the family or individual.
  Scope and Contents
  Gaming counters with identified or attributed provenance to families and individuals chiefly in Great Britain, as well as Ireland and France.
  - Adams family, London, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and a lozenge with three cats passant., circa 1760 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Verso has a floral pattern.
  - Anderson family, Edinburgh, Scotland
    - Round counter with a vine and moth border and an escutcheon with a saltire between a crescent in chief and three mullets pierced, two in fess and one in base, below a crest of an eagle on a torse and above the motto "Qui honeste fortiter.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Verso has a monogram "GWA."
  - Anderson family, Selkirkshire, Scotland
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and an escutcheon quarterly, first and fourth a saltire between two crescents in chief and base and as many mullets in flank and a bordure wavy, second and third three bucks' heads couped and attired under a crest of a sword encircled with two olive branches and above the motto "Pro bello vel pace," and flanked by a scene with a bird and ass., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Verso of three Chinese men, one man carrying a staff and another a fan, and a village scene.
  - Anderson family, attributed
    - Rectangle counter with a Queen Charlotte border and a crest of a griffin sejant on a torse., circa 1790-1840 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Verso of a Chinese man retrieving a fish trap.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a Queen Charlotte border and a crest of a griffin sejant on a torse., circa 1790-1840 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Verso of a Chinese man with a fan.
  - Arthur family, Springfield, Essex, England
    - Shuttle counter with a drilled border and a crest of a pelican in her piety feeding her young in a nest on a torse above the monogram "JA" and flanked by flowers., circa 1780-1800 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Verso has a flower and diapering.
    - Rectangle counter with a drilled border and a crest of a pelican in her piety feeding her young in a nest on a torse above the monogram "NA.", circa 1780-1800 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Verso has a flower.
      Both sides flanked by flowers.
  - Balmakin family, attributed
    - Oblong rectangle counter with deep carving an a vine and moth border and a crest of a dexter cubit arm with an index finger extended on a torse below the motto "Respice finem" and above a monogram "AB" and flanked by a scene with two birds., circa 1820-1840 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Verso of two Chinese men and a village scene.
  - Belasyse family of Yorkshire, England
    - Fish-shaped counter with a crest of a stag's head erased holding in the mouth a sprig on a torse and laurel wreath., circa 1724 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Benson family or Bewson family
    - Rectangle counter with a drilled border and an escutcheon of a chevron with three escallop shells between three goats., circa 1790-1810 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Verso has monogram "IB."
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a drilled border and an escutcheon of a chevron with three escallop shells between three goats., circa 1790-1810 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bishop of Ely, Cambridgeshire, England
    Biographical/Historical note
    Probably James Yorke (1730-1808), who served as the Bishop of Ely from 1781 until his death.
    - Rectangle counter with a Queen Charlotte border and an escutcheon with three ducal crowns below a bishop miter., circa 1790-1840 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Verso has a Chinese man seated with an iron.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a Queen Charlotte border and an escutcheon with three ducal crowns below a bishop miter., circa 1790-1840 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Verso has a Chinese man seated with a fan.
  - Blunt family, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a drilled border and a crest of a sun in glory on a torse., circa 1790-1810 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Verso of a Chinese village.
  - Bonham family, Essex, England
    - Oblong rectangle rectangle counter with a line border and a crest of a mermaid on a torse and holding in the dexter hand a mirror and in the sinister a comb and supported by mulberries., circa 1760 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Verso has mulberries.
  - Bookey and Peake family. The latter from Sandwich, Kent, England.
    Probably Captain Matthew Bookey (circa 1699-1747) of the East India Company ship Shaftesbury, and his wife, Ann Bookey (circa 1698-1753).
    - Oblong rectangle counter with an escutcheon of a bend with three martlets impaling three talbot passant below a martlet trussed., circa 1746 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Verso has a martlet trussed above a torse.
  - Bookey family
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and a crest of a dove volant holding a spring on a torse above the monogram "B.", circa 1760-1770 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Verso has diapering.
    - Rectangle counter with a line border and a crest of a dove volant holding a spring on a torse above the monogram "B.", circa 1760-1770 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Round counter with a line border and a crest of a dove volant holding a spring on a torse above the monogram "B.", circa 1760-1770 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Brown family
    - Round counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a demi-lion rampant holding in its dexter paw a fleur-de-lis on a torse above a monogram "HB" and flanked by a scene with two birds., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Verso of a Chinese woman, a Chinese woman, and a village scene.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a demi-lion rampant holding in its dexter paw a fleur-de-lis on a torse above a monogram "HB" and flanked by a scene with two birds., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a demi-lion rampant holding in its dexter paw a fleur-de-lis on a torse above a monogram "HB" and flanked by a scene with two birds., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Verso of three Chinese men and a village scene.
  - Burgoyne family of Sutton, Bedfordshire, England
    - Round counter with a line border and a crest of a talbot sejant on a torse., circa 1750 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Verso has a scene of Chinese Hongs.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and a crest of a talbot sejant on a torse., circa 1750 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and a crest of a talbot sejant on a torse., circa 1750 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Carre family, Scotland
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and a crest of a stag's head erased proper above a torse and below the motto "Tout droit.", circa 1750-1770 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Charlotte, Queen, consort of George III, King of Great Britain (1744-1818)
    - Round counter with a Queen Charlotte border and an escutcheon with the Royal Coat of Arms of the United Kingdom are impaled with the arms of the Duke of Mecklenburg-Strelitz below the crest of St Edward's Crown., circa 1780-1790 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      Verso of the crest of St Edward's Crown above the monogram "CR."
  - Cheape family, attributed
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a key fret border and a crests of a garb on a torse below the motto "Ditat virtus" and a mouse's head and neck collared and couped, flanked by two scenes, each with a bird., circa 1790-1840 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Verso of three Chinese men and a village.
    - Round counter with a key fret border and a crests of a garb on a torse below the motto "Ditat virtus" and a mouse's head and neck collared and couped, flanked by two scenes, each with a bird., circa 1790-1840 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Verso of two Chinese men, a Chinese woman, and a village.
  - Chellery family, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a drilled border and a series of concentric circles representing a gorges (whirlpool)., circa 1820-1840 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Verso of a Chinese pagoda tower.
  - Chetwode family, Warwickshire or Staffordshire, England
    - Fish-shaped counter with scales and a crest of a demi-lion issuant from a ducal coronet., circa 1720-1760 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Clayfield family, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with an escutcheon with a saltire with five roundles counterchanged below a ducal crown., circa 1730-1750 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Rectangle counter with diapering and an escutcheon with a saltire with five roundles counterchanged below a ducal crown., circa 1760-1770 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      Verso has a figure 500.
  - Clevedon family, Essex, England. Probably commemorating a marriage between a Clevedon groom and Wolrich bride.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a geometric border and an escutcheon quartered with two lions rampant, a cross, and a chevron between three swans below a crest of a leopard stantant on a coronet and above the motto "Pro rege patria et deo.", circa 1795 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Verso of a Chinese man holding a cane and picking a fruit.
  - Clifford family, Frampton-on-Severn, Gloucestershire, England.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and an escutcheon chequy on a bend three lions passant impaling a lion passant below a crest of a hand proper holding a fleur de lis above the motto "Dulcis amor patriae," and flanked by a scene with two birds., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Cricton family of Ruthven, Scotland
    - Round counter with a line border and an escutcheon with a lion rampant on a chief and three lozenges of the first., circa 1760 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      Verso has a pillar on a torse.
    - Oblong counter with a line border and an escutcheon with a lion rampant on a chief and three lozenges of the first., circa 1760 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and an escutcheon with a lion rampant on a chief and three lozenges of the first., circa 1760 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Cruttendon family, England
    - Rectangle counter with a line border and an escutcheon with a chevron between three pierced mullets below a crest of an elk's head proper on a torse., circa 1760-1770 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      Verso has a pierced mullet.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and an escutcheon with a chevron between three pierced mullets below a crest of an elk's head proper on a torse., circa 1760-1770 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Day family, England or Ireland
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a reserves border and a crest of two wings expanded on a torse above the monogram "D.", circa 1760 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      Verso has flowers.
    - Round counter with a Queen Charlotte border and an escutcheon of a chevron between three mullets below a crest of two wings expanded on a torse., circa 1760 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      Verso has a depiction of two Chinese men.
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a Queen Charlotte border and an escutcheon of a chevron between three mullets below a crest of two wings expanded on a torse., circa 1760 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      Verso has a Chinese man riding a water buffalo.
  - Deane family or Forbes family
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and a crest of a bear's head and neck couped and muzzled below the motto, "Pro Patria.", circa 1760-1770 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Dobree family, Guernsey
    - Round counter with a drilled border and a crest of a thistle vertical on a mount., circa 1790-1810 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      Verso has monogram "PED."
    - Shuttle counter with a drilled border and a crest of a thistle vertical on a mount., circa 1790-1810 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Shuttle counter with a drilled border and a crest of a thistle vertical on a mount., circa 1790-1810 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Don-Wauchope family, Berwickshire, Scotland, attributed
    - Rectangle counter with a vine and moth border and a crest of a pomegranate fruit with a ducal crown and flanked by a scene with two moths., circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      Verso of two Chinese men, one man holds a fan and the other an umbrella, and a village scene.
  - Dormer family of Wyng, Buckinghamshire, England
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and an escutcheon with ten billets (four, three, two, one) on a chief and a demi-lion rampant issuant, circa 1725 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Drummond and Fane family of Megginch, Scotland
    Probably the family of John Drummond (1754-1836) and Lady Susan Fane (1768-1793).
    - Round counter with a Queen Charlotte border and an escutcheon of a lion rampant impaling three dexter gauntlets back affrontée below a crest of two arms drawing an arrow out of a mural crown and above the motto, "Marte et arte.", circa 1790 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Drysdale family, Scotland
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a line border and a crest of an anchor and cable proper above a torse., circa 1780 (Box 1, Folder 51)
      Verso has a monogram "PSD."
  - Dundas family, Scotland
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a key fret border and a crest of a lion's head full faced looking through a bush of oak below the motto "Essayez," and flanked by inverted Chinese scenes., circa 1790-1840 (Box 1, Folder 52)
      Verso of three Chinese men and a village; two men armed with a staff and a sword.
    - Round counter with a key fret border and a crest of a lion's head full faced looking through a bush of oak below the motto "Essayez," and surrounded by a Chinese village scene., circa 1790-1840 (Box 1, Folder 53)
      Verso of three Chinese men and a village; two men holding fans.
    - Rectangle counter with a key fret border and a crest of a lion's head full faced looking through a bush of oak below the motto "Essayez," and flanked by Chinese scenes with animals.., circa 1790-1840 (Box 1, Folder 54)
      Verso of three Chinese men and a village; one man armed with a sword.
  - Dyer, William Andrew, London, England
    William Andrew Dyer (circa 1791-1872) lived at Harley Street, London, England, circa 1810. He was the son of William Dyer (died 1824) and Rebecca Russell Dyer (died 1832) and a direct descendant of Oliver Cromwell.
    - Gaming Counters Storage Box and Gaming Counters, circa 1810 (Box 2)
      General note
      Lacquer box with a gilded heraldic cartouche that depicts a crest of a lion rampant above a monogram "WAD," as well as gilding that depicts leaf, bird, and butterfly scrolls.
      The box includes five interior boxes with the same gilding, as well as six gilded trays for holding counters and six gilded trays for holding playing cards. The trays for holding playing cards are additionally decorated with depictions of playing cards for the game Pope Joan, consisting of an ace, king, knave (jack), as well as the nine of diamonds (representing the pope) and eight of diamonds, which is removed from play in the game.
      Gaming counters in the box consist of 5 large oval counters, 12 round counters and 57 oblong rectangle counters. Each counter has a drilled border and a crest of a lion rampant above a monogram "WAD." The verso of each counter depicts a different Chinese figure. Both sides of each counter are flanked by flowers.
  - Ellice family, attributed
    - Oblong rectangle counter with a geometric border and a crest of a mermaid holding a mirror with her sinister hand on a torse above a monogram "ETE.", circa 1800-1830 (Box 1, Folder 55)
      Verso of a Chinese man holding a flower.
  - Elphinstone family, Elphinstone, Stirling, Scotland
    Probably Charles Elphinstone, 10th Lord Elphinstone (1711-1781)
    - Shuttle counter with a drilled border and a crest of a lady from the middle well attired proper holding in her dexter hand a tower and in her sinister hand a laurel branch on a torse and above the monogram "CE" and flanked by flowers., circa 1780-1800 (Box 1, Folder 56)